hey what's up guys my name is aern and
welcome back to my C++ Series so in the
last video I explained why I don't like
using namespace STD if you guys haven't
checked that video out definitely do so
but I haven't actually talked about what
namespaces are in this C++ series and
because in that video I specifically
wanted to talk about the standard
namespace and why I don't like using
namespace STD but today we're going to
be talking about what namespaces are in
C++ why they're useful when I would when
I wouldn't use them why they exist and
all the different things that we can do
with them so if we jump right into this
this is the code that we had written in
that previous video where we talked
about why I don't like using namespace
everywhere and all that kind of stuff
let's talk a little bit about what we
actually see on the screen here and how
we can further extend our usage of
namespaces and why namespaces are
actually used and necessary so over here
we essentially have this issue where we
have two print functions now they do
have different signatures one of these
takes in a string one of these takes in
a con Char but if we kind of revert to
maybe both of them taking in a con Char
so if I change this string one to
actually take in a con CH pointer like
so we kind of may have an issue if we
weren't using namespaces because these
functions are identical if I just kind
of comment out this namespace apple uh
line of code here and the orange one as
well suddenly we have a little bit of an
issue if I try and I'll fix up this
error as well if I try and just compile
this by hitting contrl F7
you can see over here that I get an
error because it's telling me that this
print function that takes in a con chart
pointer already has a body because I
have two symbols with the same name and
they're identical symbols now when I say
symbols I'm talking about things like
classes functions variables constants
that kind of that kind of thing right so
we have in this case two functions
called print which take in construct
pointer and return void they have the
same signature so these two symbols are
identical we can't have two identical
symbols that's a linking error and
potentially a compilation error in there
if they're actually in the same file so
how do we fix that what if we do want to
have two print functions or what if we
use another library that has already
defined a print function but we want to
have our own print function now back in
the days of c and in fact that still is
a thing C doesn't have name spaces which
is why if you would have noticed in the
open Gil series as an example we're
using a library called glfw which is an
openg kind of windowing and context
library and input and all that kind of
stuff right but the point is gfw is a c
is a C library it's compatible with both
C and C++ because it's a C library they
can't use namespaces which is why if you
notice in that series all of the code
that we write that has something to do
with
glfw begins with like literally every
function starts with glfw and then like
the function name for example gfw in it
or or gfw create window all of that
stuff has glfw literally prepended to
the front of it with open GL it's kind
of the same thing as well we have GL and
then the symbol name so like GL begin GL
end GL gen vertex buffers that kind of
thing right we have an act the the
actual name of the library or some kind
of ID embedded into the function name so
in our code that would be the equivalent
of if I had literally written something
like apple print right and orange print
and then now you can see that okay these
two functions are different because this
is like the apple print version this is
the orange print version and that's
actually what C libraries tend to do
because they can't just you know I I
can't make a function just called init
because init is such a common name what
if you know if every library was to do
was to just name their functions init
then you could never use those libraries
together without having to modify the
source code so what they do usually is
just kind of the name of the library to
it so JFW in it and that works because
well it's a fairly unique name right JFW
in it okay cool that's specific to that
glfw library now in C++ instead of us
having to do all this we have name
spaces to solve that issue the primary
purpose of Nam spaces is to avoid naming
conflicts that's why they exist to avoid
naming conflicts okay that's it sort of
just if youve getting confused by why
namespaces exist or why they're being
used
it's because of naming we want to be
able to call symbols the same name in
different contexts so if we go back here
into apple print instead of having this
what we can do is enclose this symbol in
a namespace in this case what we write
is namespace the name of the namespace
and then just as if it was any kind of
function we surround it with curly
braces which everything in everything in
between these curly brackets is included
in that Apple namespace now personally I
like to write my bracket on the same
line as the actual namespace declaration
I don't like doing this the reason that
happens is because when we have multiple
nested name spaces it gets a little bit
messy so what I like to do is if we had
apple and then maybe like functions or
something you know I have this here and
also with the end braces instead of kind
of writing it this way which is what
Visual Studio will try try and auto
format it to I like to just have it on
the same line that way my actual
functions are one level indented and not
like two or three or four or depending
on how many Nam spaces we actually have
nested uh so that's just my personal
preference you don't have to follow that
but that's why I kind of put all this
stuff on the same line so that being
said we now have a have an apple print
function if I go over here into orange
and get rid of these comments as well we
have this orange print function I can
rename it to uh just print so we're
we're able to have two functions with
exactly the same signature in this file
and when it comes time to call it what
we do is we need to specify which one we
we need to call call so print is now
inside either the apple or the orange
namespace we have two of them so if we
want to use the one from Apple we just
type Apple colon colon and then print
this colon colon is essentially like a
namespace operator so what you do is
every kind of namespace that you as you
drill down into a namespace you just put
a colon colon and that is what I guess
enters into that namespace or allows you
to call things from that namespace the
same thing applies to static functions I
guess or symbols in classes and like
methods and classes and all that stuff a
class is kind of like a namespace it is
a it is a namespace of its own which is
why if we're accessing like an inner
class inside another class or like an
enum or you know like I gave the example
of like static functions or even
non-static functions in some cases we
use colon colon so that's what the colon
colon kind of means so this double colon
is used to uh get the print function
from the Apple uh and if we were to run
this we would just get hello printing
normally
if I want to call the orange one
obviously I type in Orange now that
whole using namespace thing that we
talked about in the last episode was
just a way to not have to write this
kind of apple or orange kind of prefix
so instead of having to do this what we
can say is that actually we're using
namespace Apple which means that
basically import everything from
namespace Apple as if I had never
specified it as a namespace so in this
case print will be used from Apple if I
want I can change it to Orange I can
also say say if we have multiple things
in here like we have print and maybe
print I don't know print again or
something uh if I have multiple
functions maybe I don't want to use
print again from Orange I I just want to
uh sorry that's that's an Apple so let's
go to using namespace Apple maybe I
don't want print again when when I put
this using namespace I don't want to use
print again I still want to specify
maybe which print again I want I just
want print to be imported so to do that
we can just write using
apple and then the function name print
okay that means that we're going to take
this from the Apple namespace
specifically but for this we'd still
have to specify that namespace like that
you can also create aliases for
namespaces by just typing in namespace
you know a equals apple or something
like that that means I can type in a
print like that instead of having it to
spell out Apple that's very useful for
when you have nested namespaces so we
can also Nest namespaces as you probably
saw earlier so we can have apple and
maybe we enclude all of our function we
enclose all of our functions inside this
function's namespace for some reason
don't ask me why just an example so we
have namespace apple we have namespace
functions and then instead of us having
to write you know Apple functions like
that or you know something like using
using namespace Apple functions like
this we could also by the way for this
example you can also split this up so
you can be like using namespace Apple
and using namespace functions which
would allow us to not have to specify
any namespace for print at all so
instead of us having to do this or in
the earlier example that we can also
just say namespace a equals Apple
functions which means that I can just
type in a print as if it was in one
namespace and I would get that result
over there okay so that's a pretty basic
example of how namespaces work um I'm
not sure if there's really anything else
that I need to talk about obviously
things like the things like this are
confined to the actual scope so in other
words a this namespace a equals Apple
functions only exists within this main
function I can't access it outside uh my
recommendation is when you do things
like this like namespace a equals blah
blah blah or using namespace whatever my
recommendation is you try and confine it
to as small a scope as possible if you
just need it inside an if statement for
example you know write your write your
declaration inside that if statement if
you just need it inside a function then
write it inside the function and then as
a last result as a last result write it
in the like kind of in the top level
file but don't try and like just you
know declare it in at the top level at
all times or in header files certainly
never do it in header files the reason
we don't want to do that is because when
we get you know if we start using
namespace everywhere then as you can
probably imagine that kind of undo all
of the helpful work that namespaces do
by avoiding naming conflicts because if
we're using it what's the point of
having our functions in namespaces if we
have to if if we use namespace anyway
right it Imports everything which means
that we might as well not be using
namespaces and we can get back to the
problem of having naming conflicts
between libraries or between our own
code so that's just a few things to
think about um I've left a link below to
the CPP reference page on namespaces
this has a few examples of what you can
actually do so there's also something
called an inline namespace which really
just kind of makes everything available
to the parent namespace uh we also have
since C++ 17 the ability to actually
specify Nam spaces kind of like this so
in this case when I had this functions
instead of having to do namespace Apple
then namespace functions I can actually
just write namespace functions like that
be aware that that's not supported by
all compilers of course and it is a new
kind of C++ thing um I recommend you
read through this page if you want to
know everything that you can do with
namespaces I've pretty much covered most
of the useful things obviously the
reason why we use namespaces is kind of
to if we are creating a library of code
or if we just have our project we want
to put it behind a namespace so that we
don't get any naming conflicts that way
I'm free to create any function that I
really want everything in the C++
standard library is behind the standard
STD namespace so obviously you're not
going to get naming conflicts like that
however if you use any kind of C code no
such thing as namespaces which means
that when you do use C code you are
potentially risking a naming conflict so
even in your C++ project I would still
use a namespace of course because if you
use any c code then that's going to be
an immediate conflict if it has the same
function name as what you're actually
declaring anyway that's namespaces leave
your thoughts below leave your thoughts
on why you use namespaces why you don't
like using namespaces where you would
where you would and all that kind of
stuff I think it's pretty clear that
when you are writing code you should be
writing it behind a namespace if it's
any kind of serious
project um if you guys enjoyed this
video please hit the like button you can
help support the series by going over to
patreon.com Theo you'll get access to
videos early and many other awesome
rewards thank you so much to all the
lovely patrons that help bring this
series to life it wouldn't be here
without you I will see you guys next
time goodbye true
[Music]